A Finding Aid to the Institute of Contemporary Arts Records, 1927-circa 1985, bulk 1947-1967, in the Archives of American Art AAA.instcona
Archives of American Art
- ICA School Files, 1945-1953; Series 5; 7 Linear feet Boxes 21-27
  - Statements of Costs - Non-Profit Institution, 1949-1950 (Box 21, Folder 25)
  - Student Cards, A-J, 1948-1949 (Box 21, Folder 26-29)
  - Student Cards, K-Z, 1948-1950 (Box 22, Folder 1-10)
  - Student Cards, Miscellaneous, 1949-1950 (Box 22, Folder 11)
  - Student Cards, Miscellaneous, 1949-1951 (Box 23, Folder 1-10)
  - Student Cards, Miscellaneous, 1949-1950 (Box 24, Folder 1)
  - Student Files, A-K, 1947-1953 (Box 24, Folder 2-17)
  - Student Files, L-Y, 1945-1952 (Box 25, Folder 1-15)
  - Student Progress Reports, 1949-1950 (Box 25, Folder 16)
  - Students Dropped, 1948-1949 (Box 25, Folder 17)
  - Students Dropped, 1948-1949 (Box 26, Folder 1-3)
  - Supply Receipts, 1951 (Box 26, Folder 4)
  - Teacher's Grade Reports (Box 26)
    - Aaron, Beatrice T., 1949-1951 (Box 26, Folder 5)
    - Aaron, David, 1948-1949 (Box 26, Folder 6)
    - Adams, James, circa 1948-1950 (Box 26, Folder 7)
    - Anderson, Alfred, 1950 (Box 26, Folder 8)
    - Barker, Howard, 1948-1949 (Box 26, Folder 9)
    - Barnes, James, circa 1948-1950 (Box 26, Folder 10)
    - Bennet, Mary Alyce, 1948-1950 (Box 26, Folder 11)
    - Boicourt, Joan, 1950-1951 (Box 26, Folder 12)
    - Bond, Robin, 1948-1950 (Box 26, Folder 13)
    - Bradshaw, Richmond, 1949 (Box 26, Folder 14)
    - Brockhuizen, 1949-1950 (Box 26, Folder 15)
    - Brostimp, John, 1950-1951 (Box 26, Folder 16)
    - Butler, circa 1950-1951 (Box 26, Folder 17)
    - Chase, R., 1950-1951 (Box 26, Folder 18)
    - Clayton, Howard, 1949 (Box 26, Folder 19)
    - Coates, P., 1951 (Box 26, Folder 20)
    - Crist, Noche, 1950-1951 (Box 26, Folder 21)
    - Donehue, Vincent, 1948-1950 (Box 26, Folder 22)
    - Donehue?, 1949-1950 (Box 26, Folder 23)
    - Evett, Robert, 1948-1951 (Box 26, Folder 24)
    - Fleming, Mary Wight, 1949-1950 (Box 26, Folder 25)
    - Fleming, Rudd, 1948-1951 (Box 26, Folder 26)
    - Gaffney, Joan, 1949-1950 (Box 26, Folder 27)
    - Giampietro, Alexander, 1949-1951 (Box 26, Folder 28)
    - Green, Robert, 1949-1950 (Box 26, Folder 29)
    - Hurwitz, Albert, 1951 (Box 26, Folder 30)
    - Jacobs, Jack, 1951 (Box 26, Folder 31)
    - Joyce, Barbara, 1948-1949 (Box 26, Folder 32)
    - Kennedy, Angela, 1949-1951 (Box 26, Folder 33)
    - Leckie, Hubert, 1948-1950 (Box 26, Folder 34)
    - McClure, Harry, 1948-1951 (Box 26, Folder 35)
    - Noland, Kenneth, 1950-1951 (Box 26, Folder 36)
    - Polich, 1949 (Box 26, Folder 37)
    - Richman, Robert, 1948-1952 (Box 26, Folder 38)
    - Roberts, Martha, 1951 (Box 26, Folder 39)
    - Rudes, Beatrice, circa 1948-1950 (Box 26, Folder 40)
    - Satterlee, Nicholas, 1949 (Box 26, Folder 41)
    - Sladen, Charles, circa 1948-1950 (Box 26, Folder 42)
    - Smull, William, 1950-1951 (Box 26, Folder 43)
    - Takeuchi, B., 1949 (Box 26, Folder 44)
    - Taylor, William, 1951 (Box 26, Folder 45)
    - Weeks, 1950 (Box 26, Folder 46)
    - Weiner, 1949 (Box 26, Folder 47)
    - Wishnow, Jack, 1951 (Box 26, Folder 48)
    - Woodley, Robert, 1950-1952 (Box 26, Folder 49)
    - Miscellaneous, 1948-1952 (Box 26, Folder 50)
  - Veterans Administration Vouchers, 1948-1952 (Box 26, Folder 51-55)
  - Class Cards, circa 1948-1951 (Box 27, Folder 2-3)
    Index cards from Box 21, Folder 6 in 2 shoeboxes
  - Literature Cards [Robert Richman], circa 1948-1951 (Box 27, Folder 4)
    Index cards from Box 21, Folder 17 in shoebox
- Administrative and Financial Files, 1945-1979; 1983; Series 6; 5.2 Linear feet Boxes 28-33, 38
  This series includes budgets and proposals; financial records such as accounting ledgers, banking records, bills, cashbooks, statements of operation, and tax records; founding documents; fundraising correspondence and records; records of grants received and grant proposals; mailing lists; membership lists; and Meridian House Foundation records. Also found are three folders originally titled "Robert Richman's Desktop;" however, based on the dates of the materials, it is likely that the material is not exclusively from his desktop.
  - Accounting Journal, 1952-1955 (Box 28, Folder 1)
  - Accounting Ledger Pages, circa 1948-circa 1952 (Box 28, Folder 2-4)
  - Accounts Payable, Bills, 1951-1952 (Box 28, Folder 5)
  - Address Referral, circa 1965 (Box 28, Folder 6)
  - American Express, circa 1966-1967 (Box 28, Folder 7)
  - Artist Payments, 1950-1954 (Box 28, Folder 8)
  - Auditoriums, 1958-1967 (Box 28, Folder 9-10)
  - Bank Statements, Canceled Checks, and Check Stubs - Riggs National Bank, 1950-1955 (Box 28, Folder 11-12)
  - Bank Statements, Canceled Checks and Check Stubs - State Savings Bank, 1953-1954 (Box 28, Folder 13-14)
  - Berckemeyer Dinners, "Facade" - Sir Osbert and Dame Edith Sitwell, 1957 (Box 28, Folder 15)
  - Bills, A-Z, 1948-1953 (Box 28, Folder 16-31)
  - Bills, 1963-1964 (Box 28, Folder 32)
  - Bills, A-K (1966-1967), 1948; 1964-1967 (Box 28, Folder 33-35)
  - Bills, L-Z (1966-1967), 1960-1967 (Box 29, Folder 1-3)
  - Bills, A-Z (1967-1968), 1965-1968 (Box 29, Folder 4-10)
  - Bills, Miscellaneous, circa 1951-1952 (Box 29, Folder 11)
  - Bills, Paid in Full, 1951-1952 (Box 29, Folder 12)
  - Board of Trustees, circa 1952-1959 (Box 29, Folder 13-14)
  - [Book Project, Huntington Cairns?], 1945-1979 (Box 29, Folder 15)
  - BSP (Benefactors, Sponsors, Patrons and Contributions), circa 1964-1967 (Box 29, Folder 16)
  - BSP (Box 29)
    - 1965 Ask, 1965-1966 (Box 29, Folder 17)
    - Address Lists [and Contributions], 1965 (Box 29, Folder 18)
    - Annual Statement of Operations, 1961-1962 (Box 29, Folder 19)
    - "The ICA in the Nation's Capital: The Fifteen Years - A History", 1962 (Box 29, Folder 20)
    - Letters, 1961-1967 (Box 29, Folder 21-25)
    - Promotion, 1954-1959 (Box 29, Folder 26)
    - Promotion Letters, 1961-1962 (Box 29, Folder 27)
  - Budgets (1950-1951), 1948-1949 (Box 29, Folder 28)
    Oversized material housed in Box 38, Folder 1
  - Budgets, 1950-1960s (Box 29, Folder 29-30)
    Oversized material housed in Box 38, Folder 2
  - Budgets and Fundraising, 1954-1961 (Box 29, Folder 31)
  - Budgets and Proposals, 1960s (Box 29, Folder 32-33)
  - Budgets and Proposals, 1960s (Box 30, Folder 1)
  - Canceled Checks, 1968 (Box 30, Folder 2)
  - Cash Receipts from "Orfeo", 1958 (Box 30, Folder 3)
  - Cashbook, 1952-1957 (Box 30, Folder 4)
  - Cashbook Entries, 1957-1958 (Box 30, Folder 5)
  - Checks and Deposits, 1956-1957 (Box 30, Folder 6)
  - Contributions, circa 1957-1977 (Box 30, Folder 7)
  - Cost of Printed Materials, 1960s (Box 30, Folder 8)
  - Cultural Officers, circa 1960-1961 (Box 30, Folder 9)
  - D.C. Arts Application, 1966 (Box 30, Folder 10)
  - Endowments and Contributions, 1948-1953 (Box 30, Folder 11)
  - Fifteenth Year History, 1962; 1958 (Box 30, Folder 12)
  - Financial Notes Payable to M&R, 1960s (Box 30, Folder 13)
  - Foreign Artists Appointments (1960-1961) (Box 30, Folder 14)
  - Founding Documents, 1948; 1959-1962 (Box 30, Folder 15)
  - Founding Documents, King-Smith School of Creative Arts, 1947 (Box 30, Folder 16)
  - Funding, The Ford Foundation, 1958-1967 (Box 30, Folder 17-33)
  - Funding, ICA Corporate, 1962-1965 (Box 30, Folder 34)
  - Funding, J.D. Rockefeller III Fund, 1965-1966 (Box 30, Folder 35)
  - Funding, The Meyer Foundation, 1954-1965 (Box 30, Folder 36-39)
  - Funding, The Meyer Foundation, 1965 (Box 31, Folder 1)
  - Funding, Miscellaneous Foundations and Materials, 1958-1966; 1983 (Box 31, Folder 2)
  - Funding, Old Dominion Foundation, 1948-1966 (Box 31, Folder 3-6)
  - Funding, The Whitney Foundation, 1957-1966 (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Fundraising, 1959-1962 (Box 31, Folder 8)
  - Gallery Space, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 31, Folder 9)
  - General Ledger, 1949-1950 (Box 31, Folder 10)
  - Insurance Claims and Policies, 1966-1967 (Box 31, Folder 11)
  - Lists of Contacts, 1946-1962 (Box 31, Folder 12-14)
  - Mailing Lists, 1963-1964 (Box 31, Folder 15)
  - Members' Passes Proposal, 1957 (Box 31, Folder 16)
  - Membership Lists, 1949-1951 (Box 31, Folder 17)
  - Memberships and Contributions Ledger Pages, 1957-1958 (Box 31, Folder 18)
  - Memo [Richman's Handwritten Notes], circa 1961 (Box 31, Folder 19)
  - Meridian House Foundation (Box 31)
    - Belmont Annex Remodeling, 1963-1967 (Box 31, Folder 20)
    - Correspondence, 1962-1967 (Box 31, Folder 21)
    - FY1960-1968 (Box 31, Folder 22-29)
    - ICA Space, 1960-1969 (Box 31, Folder 30-32)
    - Report on Examination, 1967 (Box 31, Folder 33)
    - Reports, Memos and Minutes, 1963-1969 (Box 31, Folder 34)
  - Meridian House Foundation, Reports, Memos and Minutes, 1960-1968 (Box 32, Folder 1-3)
  - Meridian House Foundation I, 1959-1960 (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Meridian House Foundation II, 1960-1966 (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Meridian House Foundation III, 1962-1967 (Box 32, Folder 6-7)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Records and Notes, circa 1949-1960s (Box 32, Folder 8-9)
    Includes financials regarding José Limón performance
  - Pending File, 1957-1966 (Box 32, Folder 10)
  - Performances, 1951-1954 (Box 32, Folder 11)
  - Personnel, 1959-1965 (Box 32, Folder 12-13)
  - Petty Cash, 1966-1968 (Box 32, Folder 14-15)
  - Programs Income and Expenses Analysis, 1963-1967 (Box 32, Folder 16)
  - Publications, ICA, circa 1950s-1978 (Box 32, Folder 17-18)
  - Receipts, 1965-1966 (Box 32, Folder 19)
  - Records of Growth, 1957-1958 (Box 32, Folder 20)
  - Richman, Robert, Desktop, 1946-1962 (Box 32, Folder 21-23)
  - Richman, Robert, Notes and Miscellaneous, 1946-1970s (Box 32, Folder 24-27)
  - The Riggs National Bank, 1958-1967; 1949 (Box 32, Folder 28-29)
  - Shipping and Insurance, 1946-1951 (Box 32, Folder 30)
  - Statements of Operations, 1957-1961 (Box 32, Folder 31)
  - Summary of Budgeted Expenses (FY1962-1966), circa 1961 (Box 32, Folder 32)
  - Tax Exemption, 1948; 1960s (Box 32, Folder 33)
  - Taxes, Payroll, 1961; 1967-1968 (Box 33, Folder 1)
  - Trustees Report, 1959 (Box 33, Folder 2)
  - Visiting Artists and Professors Program, 1955-1968 (Box 33, Folder 3)
  - Oversized Ledger Pages, Budget (1950-1951), 1948-1949 (Box 38, Folder 1)
    Oversized material from Box 29, Folder 28
  - Oversized Ledger Pages, Budget, 1950s-1960s (Box 38, Folder 2)
    Oversized material from Box 29, Folder 29
- Printed Materials, 1945-1970; Series 7; 2.9 Linear feet Boxes 33-35, 38
  Found are comprehensive printed materials from 1947-1967 for ICA's programs, including program calendars, exhibition announcements, invitations, membership forms, and press releases. Also found are newspaper clippings regarding performance and exhibition reviews, arts funding, the current state of the arts, and articles related to artists; and three oversized clippings scrapbooks. There is scattered printed material from other organizations, indicated as such on folder titles.
  Folders are arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Announcements, 1958-1966 (Box 33, Folder 4)
  - Announcements, King-Smith School of Creative Arts, circa 1947 (Box 33, Folder 5)
  - Announcements, Phillips Gallery, 1955 April-May (Box 33, Folder 6)
  - Art News, 1950 (Box 33, Folder 7)
  - Articles, circa 1954 (Box 33, Folder 8)
  - Brochure, Center of Creative Arts, Adelphi College, 1947 (Box 33, Folder 9)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets, ICA, circa 1947-1962 (Box 33, Folder 10)
  - Brochures and Pamphlets, IIE, 1956-1958 (Box 33, Folder 11)
  - Galleries and Exhibitions, 1948-1964 (Box 33, Folder 12-13)
  - ICA Development and Plan [Miscellaneous Printed Material], 1960-1966 (Box 33, Folder 14)
  - ICA Season 1947-1953 Printed Materials (Box 33, Folder 15)
  - ICA Season 1954-1955 Printed Materials (Box 33, Folder 16)
  - ICA Season 1955-1956 Printed Materials (Box 33, Folder 17)
  - ICA Season 1956-1957 Printed Materials (Box 33, Folder 18)
  - ICA Season 1957-1958 Printed Materials (Box 33, Folder 19)
  - ICA Season 1958-1959 Printed Materials (Box 33, Folder 20)
  - ICA Season 1959-1960 Printed Materials (Box 33, Folder 21)
  - ICA Season 1960-1961 Printed Materials (Box 33, Folder 22)
  - ICA Season 1961-1962 Printed Materials (Box 33, Folder 23)
  - ICA Season 1962-1963 Printed Materials (Box 33, Folder 24)
  - ICA Season 1963-1964 Printed Materials (Box 33, Folder 25-26)
  - ICA Season 1964-1965 Printed Materials (Box 34, Folder 1-2)
  - ICA Season 1965-1966 Printed Materials (Box 34, Folder 3)
  - ICA Season 1966-1967 Printed Materials (Box 34, Folder 4)
  - Inserts and Enclosures, 1964-1966 (Box 34, Folder 5)
  - Invitations, 1960s (Box 34, Folder 6)
  - Literature and Pamphlets, 1950s-1960s (Box 34, Folder 7)
  - Magazines, 1950 (Box 34, Folder 8)
  - Memoriams and Dedications, 1963-1965 (Box 34, Folder 9)
  - Miscellaneous, ICA, circa 1947-1970 (Box 34, Folder 10-11)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1945-1967 (Box 34, Folder 12-26)
    Oversized material housed in Box 38, Folder 3
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1961-1967 (Box 35, Folder 1-11)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Historic Presidential Events, 1945; 1960 (Box 35, Folder 12)
  - Playbills, 1962 April (Box 35, Folder 13)
  - Press Releases, circa 1947-1952 (Box 35, Folder 14)
  - Press Releases, Other Galleries, 1964 (Box 35, Folder 15)
  - Program Calendars, 1952-1968 (Box 35, Folder 16-17)
  - Programs in Dance, 1961-1968; 1946-1947 (Box 35, Folder 18-19)
  - Programs in Music and Dance from India, 1960s (Box 35, Folder 20)
  - Programs in Music, Theater and Seminars, 1947-1967 (Box 35, Folder 21-22)
  - Programs in Painting (U.S. and Foreign), 1946-1964 (Box 35, Folder 23-24)
  - Programs in Sculpture and Pottery, 1948-1965 (Box 35, Folder 25)
  - Scrapbooks of Newspaper Clippings [3 books], 1962-1967; 1958-1959 (Box 35, Folder 26)
    Oversized material housed in Box 38, Folders 4-6
  - Stationary, circa 1967-1968 (Box 35, Folder 27)
  - Oversized Newspaper Clippings, 1957 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    Oversized material from Box 34, Folder 19
  - Oversized Newspaper Clippings, Historic Presidential Events, 1945; 1960 (Box 38, Folder 3)
    Oversized material from Box 35, Folder 12
  - Oversized Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings, 1958-1959 (Box 38, Folder 4)
    Oversized material from Box 35, Folder 26
  - Oversized Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings, 1964-1965 (Box 38, Folder 5)
  - Oversized Scrapbook of Newspaper Clippings, 1962-1967 (Box 38, Folder 6)
- Photographs, circa 1930s-1960s; circa 1985; Series 8; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 35-36
  This series includes black and white photographs and negatives of people, most of whom are unidentified. People identified include e.e. cummings, Aldous Huxley, Sir Herbert Read, Maida Richman, Robert Richman, and Frank Lloyd Wright. The photographs dated circa 1985 are reprints of negatives requested by AAA staff.
  - Exhibitions, circa 1950s (Box 35, Folder 28)
  - Gabo, Naum, Sculptures, circa 1930s-1950s (Box 35, Folder 29)
  - Gray, Cleve, Artwork, circa 1950s (Box 35, Folder 30)
  - People, circa 1985; circa 1930s-1950s (Box 35, Folder 31-34)
  - Richman, Robert?, circa 1960 (Box 35, Folder 35)
  - Theater Publicity, circa 1950s (Box 36, Folder 1)
  - Negatives, People, circa 1947-1960s (Box 36, Folder 2)
  - Negatives, [Francesco Sforza?], circa 1947-1960s (Box 36, Folder 3)
- Personal Papers of Robert Richman, 1940s-1980; Series 9; 0.4 Linear feet Boxes 36-37
  Robert Richman's personal papers includes personal correspondence, correspondence related to "New Republic," handwritten and typed writings, some bills, and his curriculum vitae.
  - "The Arts at Mid-Century", 1953-1955 (Box 36, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1946-1959 (Box 36, Folder 5-6)
  - Correspondence and Notes, 1953-1977 (Box 36, Folder 7)
  - Cranberry Island, Maine, 1970s-1980 (Box 36, Folder 8)
  - Curriculum Vitae, circa 1964-1970 (Box 36, Folder 9)
  - The Japan-America Society, Hamada, 1979 (Box 36, Folder 10)
  - "New Republic", 1950-1954 (Box 36, Folder 11)
  - Notes, Robert Richman, 1946-circa 1960s (Box 36, Folder 12)
  - Paid Bills, Personal, 1967-1968 (Box 36, Folder 13)
  - Writings, Others, circa 1950 (Box 36, Folder 14)
  - Writings, Poetry, 1940s-1950 (Box 37, Folder 1-2)
  - Writings, Sir Herbert Read, "The Limits of Painting", circa 1962 (Box 37, Folder 3)
  - Writings, Robert Richman [and Donohue?], circa 1940s-1950s (Box 37, Folder 4)